Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
It's exactly because she has your trust
that I must treat her generously.
How about granting her the title of Attendant, just like when you entered the palace?
I'll name her Attendant Xi [Auspicious].
Your Majesty, I dare not ...
How could I deserve the honor of serving Your Majesty?
I beg Your Majesty to forgive me.
How strange.
Any maid in the palace would thank the Buddha
for receiving such favor and honor,
but you’re not willing.
I admit my offense, Your Majesty.
I already ...
have someone in my heart.
You have someone in your heart?
A guard, or an imperial doctor? Tell me.
If this marriage is fated, I will decree it.
I want to keep Jade by my side
until the day I arrange her marriage myself.
Jade.
Bring Hongyan from the Imperial Nursery.
His Majesty wants to see him.
Yes.
I like to see you being jealous.
Since Consort Vertu passed,
your heart has been heavy.
It’s rare to hear a few lighthearted words from you.
My sorrow is not the most important thing.
Gūwalgiya "created winds and waves" in the harem,
which caused Meizhuang's prenatal shock
and then bleeding to death.
Don’t worry.
I will respond to this in time.
I hope so.
Or Meizhuang still won't be able to close her eyes
"under the Yellow Springs."
At the court this morning,
Gūwalgiya Emin said since I have four sons,
I should consider designating the eldest as Crown Prince,
to consolidate the nation's foundation.
Whoever suggested that should be flogged at court immediately.
Even flogging to death isn’t too harsh!
Your Majesty is in your prime.
Why mention the nation's foundation right now?
That’s extremely inappropriate.
Being designated as Crown Prince too early
means being a target to all.
It would encourage the princes to have their eyes upon the crown
instead of concentrating on their studies.
Furthermore, our tradition is to select
the most virtuous, not simply the eldest.
Why "wag their tongues" about their ages?
By the way,
the Fourth Prince has been diligent in his studies.
Has Your Majesty questioned him on his schoolwork?
He's all right. He can answer quite smoothly.
However,
I believe our child will be better -
Hongyan will be even better.
The Empress has a gentle heart.
She made the unwise decision to add alum
to the water for the blood droplet test
to confuse the others,
largely because Your Majesty favors the youngest son so much.
Even now, I’m frightened when I recall that day.
So I request Your Majesty be less partial to Hongyan.
The Empress was worried. I understand that.
Although Hongshi isn’t outstanding,
how could I not care for him? He’s also my child.
I’d better appoint a marriage for him,
which may also relieve the Empress's unease.
I haven’t yet dared tell Imperial Mother that
the Empress also took part in that incident.
She secretly changed the water for the blood droplet test,
conspiring to frame the Noble Consort and the Sixth Prince.
You don’t need to tell me.
These days,
you won't take a single step into her palace.
In my heart, I already "knew the numbers."
Since the Noble Consort got pregnant and returned,
even I had a shadow of misgiving in my mind,
let alone other people.
The imperial bloodline must be pure.
Not a hint of doubt can be allowed.
The Empress manages the palace affairs.
She’s obliged to investigate.
The blood testing method was at fault -
since the water was easily contaminated with alum -
and that nearly wrongly accused the Noble Consort.
Emperor, you can blame her for incompetence,
but you cannot accuse her of conspiracy.
I know.
Not for any other reason,
but because she is the sister of your most beloved.
You can distrust Yixiu,
but you can't distrust Première.
True.
The Empress is the mother of the country.
The people are uneasy when the mother of the country is uneasy.
If the Emperor always appears
with a favored concubine instead of the Empress,
that concubine may harbor ideas of reaching beyond her station.
If one day, a concubine rises above the Empress,
then the imperial harem, even the
entire country, will be in chaos.
Yes.
"One's words are kinder when death is nearer."
I'm near the end of my life.
You need to remember, Emperor,
no matter how good your Noble Consort is,
there is only one Empress.
Elder Sister!
We come to the garden every day,
either to see the flowers or net butterflies.
I'm getting so bored!
Outsiders think the Forbidden City is full of
unlimited imperial wealth and luxury.
Only insiders know there's no place more tedious
than the square-shaped sky inside these high walls.
Right?
What are you two sisters talking about?
Sounds like a lively discussion.
- Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
- Peace to Your Majesty.
My sister-in-law is here too. What a coincidence!
I thank Your Majesty.
The weather is getting hotter lately.
Are you accustomed to living in the palace?
If there's any discomfort, just tell your sister.
Consider the palace as your home.
Yurao has stayed in the palace for quite some time now.
Although living in the palace is different from at home,
she's gotten used to it.
There was some good first-flush Dragon Well tea
offered as a tribute.
I'll send some to you.
I wonder if your sister likes it.
I thank Your Majesty for caring.
Everything in the palace is grand and majestic,
with beautiful ladies in abundance.
Everything is extraordinary,
except that I always have to obey the rules.
Unlike at home, where I have no rules.
For example, in ordinary families,
I would call you my brother-in-law.
However, in the palace, I must always remember that
Your Majesty has heavenly authority and I musn't give offense.
I have to be prudent and cautious all the time,
so, the palace doesn't feel like home.
Listen to that!
You have great rhetorical skills.
But compared to your sister, I'm afraid you have to admit defeat.
Here she is: complaining that the palace
is not as comfortable as home,
but, I just can't get upset with her.
I'm no match for Yurao's rhetorical skills.
I've been wondering what kind of future brother-in-law
will be able to tame her sharp tongue.
Your sister just recently returned.
Why are you in such a hurry to marry her off?
I suggest she stay around for a couple more years
since she's still young.
She should take her time to select the best for her.
If my sister-in-law finds the palace too constraining,
I just remembered Yunxi came to the palace today, and
he suggested going to the Summer Palace for archery
since the weather is good.
Noble Consort Lumière, will you keep me company?
And my sister-in-law will join us too.
No matter who he is,
I'm not interested if he's not a good archer.
Yurao agrees to go.
Your Majesty's idea is wonderful.
It's a rare opportunity to see Venerable Prince Shen.
Please allow us to get changed before joining Your Majesty's procession.
Good.
Here.
Bravo!
Yunxi is getting better and better with his horseback archery.
Our father taught Yunli horseback archery personally,
but now he is so out of practice that
he is worse than when he was seven or eight.
Your Majesty,
I got rusty from "drinking alone with the moon" too much.
Whereas Your Majesty has assiduously maintained your skills in archery.
Our 17th brother is still not married.
When he is, his hands and feet will be even softer.
I wouldn't have drunk if I knew you were going to make fun of me.
I was already light-headed before shooting the arrow.
Fill up.
My offense deserves death.
Don't worry, it's just a piece of clothing.
I'll get changed in the side chamber.
What's that?
Give it to me.
Our 17th brother must have had a romance somewhere.
Otherwise he wouldn't carry a girl's trinket around!
This paper-cut portrait ...
looks like Noble Consort Lumière.
That's quite a resemblance.
Unfounded allegations -
I have experienced too many this year.
It is just a small portrait.
What makes Your Majesty think it is me?
This small image does look a bit like Noble Consort Lumière.
But doesn’t Your Majesty think
it also resembles Yurao or Jade?
The girl in the portrait looks happy and displeased at the same time.
The more I look at it, the more I think it resembles Yurao.
In a month it will be the Qixi Festival.
[Chinese Valentine's Day]
Will Your Majesty give this story a happy ending?
But…
Yurao and Yunli just met for the first time.
The edges of this image are slightly discolored.
Yunli must have held it in his hand and looked at it many times.
My sister-in-law came to the palace a few months ago.
She didn’t met Yunli until today.
It’s not her.
I beg Your Majesty's forgiveness for my capital offense.
This ...
is my image.
Really?
It was seven years ago,
I put it in this tasseled sachet.
When Consort Fleur ordered Her Highness to be
punished by kneeling in the Palace of Earthly Honor,
I met Lord XVII, so I asked him for help.
After that, I went to the Hall of Converging Light to extend my gratitude.
You did?
When I was in the Hall of Converging Light,
I saw some pieces of colored paper on the table.
On a whim, I cut some window flowers
as a thank-you gift for His Lordship.
Then, His Lordship asked me if I knew how to cut a portrait.
So I cut out an image in my own likeness
and put it into this sachet.
On another day, His Lordship met me.
He asked me my favorite flower, and
I told him I like pollia.
Your Majesty can see if there are
a few petals of pollia in the sachet.
Exactly so.
If it wasn't your image,
how would you know what is inside?
Huan Huan, have you known her heart?
I am such a fool.
She put herself through a lot hiding it from me.
I've noticed that you wear an azalea in your hair every day.
Why? Do you prefer azalea,
rather than pollia?
That is because His Lordship said that
I look pleasing with azalea blooms in my hair.
So…
So I ...
A few months ago, whenever I visited Consort Lumière’s palace,
I didn’t see Jade.
I heard that when Lord XVII was sick,
it was Jade who took care of him.
I was confused at the time.
It turns out there is this fated relationship!
No wonder.
That's why you dropped the tray in fright that day,
when I teased Noble Consort Lumière
that I would promote you to Attendant.
And that's also why,
Yunli never even considered having a Lord Consort.
Given my humble status, I dare not "climb on a high branch."
Yet...
I've heard that his Lordship's garden has
planted plums with jade-colored blossoms.
I haven't had the honor to see them.
I only wish that I'll be able to look at them some day,
then I shall be happy and content.
If you two keep on waiting,
I'm afraid you'll be waiting for another seven years!
Here, today I'll make a ruling:
Jade is granted marriage with you.
Your Majesty -
Your Majesty, with my lowly status,
how do I deserve the honor to serve His Lordship?
If Yunli didn't tell you,
how could you know about those jade-colored plum blossoms?
Also, your name is "Jade"!
Yunli needs someone to take care of his estate affairs.
For years, you have served Noble Consort Lumière attentively.
You -
have my trust.
Your Majesty, it does seem improper
if Jade is granted to His Lordship like this.
When she enter's His Lordship's estate,
will she be a concubine, consort, or the primary wife?
It's already an excessive honor
for a dowry maid of Her Noble Highness to serve His Lordship.
Your Majesty, after I left the palace and went to the temple,
I had only Jade and Jinxi to share the "frosts and storms."
Jade grew up with me, and we're as close as sisters.
Your Majesty, since His Lordship has cherished Jade for seven years,
I believe, it's because he didn't want her to be treated poorly.
What do you propose?
I request to take Jade as my honorary sister
and record her name in the pedigree book
as the second daughter of the Niohuru family,
so she can gloriously marry into His Lordship's estate as the primary wife.
Your Noble Highness must know your care for Jade has its limits.
When all the lords' wives come to the palace in the future,
should Jade be on equal footing with us imperial concubines?
My Lady, I understand you care for me deeply,
but the title doesn't matter to me.
Please don't worry over me.
Jade,
you know not the whispers of the crowd.
If you enter His Lordship's estate without a good title and name,
when people talk about this,
some may kindly say you've been cherished by His Lordship for years;
that your fate was granted.
But others may maliciously speak of pre-marital intercourse.
It will ruin both of your reputations for nothing.
Your Majesty,
please excuse my obstinence, but I cannot take Jade as my primary wife.
Many years ago,
I met a lady ...
our hearts were committed.
Later on, we were parted with a thousand miles between us,
and we weren't able to marry.
Yet in my heart,
she is my only wife.
Jade is a good girl,
but I can never take her as my primary wife.
I hope Noble Consort Lumière can understand.
I leave the decision to Your Majesty.
I only ask that Jade is not mistreated.
I permit your request.
Jade will become the second daughter of Niohoru
and marry Noble Prince Guo as his Lord Consort.
I thank your Majesty.
- Congratulations, Lord XVII. Congratulations, Jade.
- You may rise!
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Here's to Your Majesty.
My Lady, you are tipsy.
Let me take you for a walk to sober up.
Jade, allow me.
Careful.
These hands,
this person,
all belong to Jade from now on.
I know your heart is heavy,
but I feel even worse than you do!
Today we celebrate this joyous occasion.
Tomorrow you will be my brother-in-law.
Does it have to be like this?
You see,
the moon is destined to sink in the west.
There's no other path
for you and I to follow.
If we do not obey,
there will be more than our own deaths to pay.
The rumors alone....
Wen Shichu is the example before us.
I can't let you be dragged down.
I hated myself
for not being able to come to your aid that day.
If you were the one that had been accused,
I'm afraid I would have gone mad.
Jade has always been fond of you.
Her affection for you
is no less than mine.
I knew that a long time ago.
Don't fail her.
You know me.
I only want you.
Today is the border of our lives.
Before, all you had was me.
From now on and after, there's only Jade.
To tell you the truth,
Jade is not just "my honorary sister,"
she is my sister by blood.
My father loved her mother dearly.
But since her mother was the daughter of a guilty official,
father had to hide the truth.
Jade could not be acknowledged by our ancestors.
You must treat her well.
The Empress Dowager is gravely ill.
It's good to have a wedding to drive away any misfortune.
Even though family status is mismatched in this marriage,
you two have genuine feelings for each other.
I follow Your Majesty's arrangement.
Speaking of family status ...
reminds me of something.
Several years ago,
the Empress Dowager wanted to arrange a marriage for you.
She's very fond of Meng Jingxian, the daughter of Duke of Pei.
She met you once when you were young,
and she's been devoted for a long time.
But you never agreed to the marriage.
Meng Jingxian is so committed she refuses to marry anyone else.
Biding her time has left her as his only unmarried daughter.
When the news of you having a Lord Consort spread,
grief overcame her ...
and she's become
too ill to get out of bed.
The Duke of Pei earnestly loves his daughter
and sent three memorandums to me,
begging me to have mercy on his daughter's devotion.
He's willing to let her be a concubine
to serve by the side of Noble Prince Guo.
So he will not lose his daughter at his advanced age.
Imperial Brother, you are wise to see that
I really do not want to marry someone else.
And we have no genuine feelings for each other.
It'd cause regrets in her life...
The Duke of Pei has served the reigns of two emperors.
He used such humble words for the love of his daughter,
even I can't help being moved by him.
Besides, it's quite common
for a man to have several concubines.
I have thought it through.
I'll let Lady Meng and Jade both be your Lord Consorts.
But I have kept her from happiness for so many years,
why should I drag her down for a lifetime?
In a nobleman's marriage,
all other matters take precedence over a true heart.
I want you to marry her
to pacify the heart of a veteran official.
If you really don't like her,
consider it as keeping one more person at home.
Why let her illness take her life away?
If Duke of Pei develops a grudge because of this,
it's not good for the peace in the court.
If you say so,
I must provide for her for life.
I will treat her well.
That's what I want to hear.
Then I also have one request, Your Majesty.
Speak.
I request Your Majesty's decree
that I will not marry again all my life.
Also, I want Jade to manage the estate affairs.
You already have your favorite before your wedding.
Lady Meng is in ill health,
so Jade should take charge of household affairs.
There are six protocols in the marriage of a lord consort:
Betrothal, requesting the bride's name and horoscope,
ancestral fortune-telling on the horoscope,
sending gifts, selecting an auspicious date,
and the marriage ceremony.
All the other protocols have been arranged,
but the bride's name ...
The family name is Niohuru. As an honarary daughter,
the daughters of my family
are given names starting with the character "Yu" or "Nü".
The household department has prepared
several names with "Yu".
If you please, Jade, you can pick one name for yourself.
Jade, take a look,
which one do you like?
All are good names with "Yu".
Yuqin, Yuyin, Yuqiao.
Why are there only names with "Yu" but not "Nü"?
It doesn't sound like the birth daughters of the Niohuru family.
The Ministry of Rites said that an honorary daughter
is not originally from the family,
and there needs to be a difference,
so the names can only start with "Yu".
The imperial doctor said
father is basically recovered from his illness.
The most important thing is that your mother enters the ancestral shrine.
Then, I choose Yuyin [hidden jade].
Her Noble Highness told us,
added to the dowry from the Household Department,
the Palace of Eternal Longevity will give
three times that dowry for Yuyin's wedding.
The wedding will be hosted by Consort Estime.
The maid formerly from the Zhen family, Bin'er,
will accompany Yuyin to manage the estate affairs.
I won't let your dowry be less
than that of the Duke of Pei's daughter.
You won't feel inferior before her.
Thank you, My Lady.
The wedding date is set for the 4th of the 6th month.
Soon it will be arranged for Your Noble Highness's
parents to visit the palace.
Huan'er.
Peace to father and mother.
Peace to Your Noble Highness.
Your Noble Highness
cannot bow to us like this.
Forgive me for being unfilial.
Bearing the name of Niohuru,
I cannot receive you in the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
As long as we're together as a family,
it doesn't matter where we meet.
Let's get up.
Everyone, get up.
Come, get up.
Come, sit.
So many years have passed.
Mother has so much white hair now.
After many years of suffering,
we finally reached the end.
When our family declined,
I was so afraid of implicating you.
We're family.
We don't use such words among ourselves.
Now everything is all right.
And now Yuyin is going to marry.
Yuyin marrying into a good family -
her mother
can now rest in peace "under the Nine Springs."
Although she will be a secondary wife,
Yuyin truly loves His Lordship,
so this has fulfilled her wish.
Given everything,
you must have put forth a lot of effort
to arrange this for her.
It's not a long-term solution for you both to stay at the inn.
His Majesty has already ordered the renovation of the Zhen estate.
You can live in peace and comfort as your age reaches what Heaven granted.
His Majesty permitted us to visit the palace -
this is already Heaven's grace.
How can we hold lofty hopes to be allowed
to stay for long in the capital?
Seeing you and the grandchildren are all well,
I feel deep consolation,
and don't hope for anything else.
Now that you're back,
I won't let you be sent back to the "barren hills and wild rivers."
While you're back in the capital,
I will plead with His Majesty to thoroughly investigate
what happened back then.
I thought
My Second Lady always liked to wear jade-green clothes.
But you look much better in red.
It's a pity that I'm just a Lord Consort,
so I cannot wear primary red.
Very beautiful - You look very good.
Thank you, elder sister, for arranging everything for me.
Tomorrow is the wonderful day.
Lord XVII doesn't have a primary wife.
You and Meng Jinxian are on equal footing.
Don't take any insult lying down,
but don't "meet a knife with another blade."
Just live your days in peace.
His Lordship said
that you will manage the estate affairs.
Temper justice with mercy.
Treat everyone properly - from the highest to the lowest.
I'm sorry, elder sister.
This should be your place,
and I took it from you.
My place is as His Majesty's Noble Consort Lumière.
How did you take my place?
You're getting married tomorrow.
You should be happy.
Don't overwork your heart.
Elder sister,
I know your heart is suffering...
A bride should be happy.
How can you cry?
Elder sister, have you ever regretted ...
If back then,
we waited for a few more months...
Then it wouldn't be me ... marrying His Lordship now.
Once one chooses a path,
there is no turning back.
It's too difficult to survive in the palace.
I don't have the time or the heart for regret.
Your future path is what you have chosen today.
I hope you will walk on without any regret.
Elder sister, I am afraid.
I'm afraid that His Lordship will always have only you in his heart.
I don't even know how to be his Lord Consort.
I'm already an outsider.
The estate is headed by you and Noble Prince Guo as a married couple.
How to do anything - is up to you.
I can only tell you: a true heart.
A true heart is the most important.
Elder sister.
I will give my whole heart to His Lordship.
I will be filial to the Consort Dowager.
You need only remember
from now on, both you and I
are shouldering the burden of the Zhen clan.
Remember,
you're His Lordship's Lord Consort.
Niohuru Yuyin bows and bids farewell to Noble Consort Lumière.
Look after yourself.
It's the auspicious hour.
Everything is ready in His Lordship's estate.
The procession from the Duke of Pei has departed.
My Second Lady may go now.
Go.
I'd rather it were you.
At least he would be happy for real.
Yuyin is more fortunate than I.
He is marrying two at once,
but desires neither.
Lift the sedan!
The unceasing cycle of yin and yang yields errors.
This is nothing unusual.
[double happiness]
Congratulations!
Drink up!
Congratulations, Noble Prince Guo! Congratulations!
Come on! Drink, drink!
- How fortunate!
- Exactly, two ladies at once!
Isn't he lucky! Congratulations!
Congratulations! Congratulations! Congratulations!
So happy for you!
Congratulations and congratulations!
Your Lordship! Your Lordship!
Let's get up.
Don't touch me!
I'm all right.
All right...
Your Lordship, you still need to give your word -
which lady's chamber will you stay at tonight?
Your Lordship, it's your joyous night,
you can't avoid both chambers!
Your Lordship, Your Lordship...
Ja... Jade...
Yes! To the Evergreen Chamber!
Your Lordship.
My Lady, it's time to sleep.
The light in the Evergreen Chamber has already been extinguished.
I'll see how things unfold now that I am married.
This is only the first night.
Madam, you are already sighing.
There will be more sighs in the days to come.
I know you have me in your heart,
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.